Kassoy, Bernard Slides and Photographs 6385 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Bernard Kassoy Slides and Photographs
1942-2007
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Kassoy, Bernard
6385 P
8.17 cubic feet
8.2 linear ft.
Photographs, 35mm slides.
8507521
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, July 07, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 23, 2015
Biographical / Historical
Bernard (Bernie) Kassoy (1914-2008) graduated from the City College of New York and Cooper Union Art School and worked in a wide range of media as a painter, printmaker, photographer, sculptor and cinematographer. As a young artist, Kassoy began his career in the WPA New York City Federal Art Project in 1936 and was arrested under the name "Michelangelo Buonarotti" at the first sit-down strike against the WPA by the Artists Union. He was also a US delegate to the 1983 International Association of Artists conference in Finland.
In 1939 Kassoy was hired as a New York City high school fine arts teacher where he taught until he retired in 1972. He also taught adult education classes on cinematography at the High School of Music and Art. As a member of the American Federation of Teachers Local 5, he created cartoons for their publication "The New York Teacher News," directed the Teachers Union art gallery, and made stage sets for theatrical productions.
Bernie Kassoy's 136 editorial cartoons preserved by the Kheel Center were largely created in the 1950s at a time when many US policy makers were enthralled by the search for Communist Party members and sympathizers. In pithy cartoons he portrayed the struggles of New York City students and teachers, as well as the Teachers Union's response to these hardships. He accused school, city, and state officials of turning their attention away from funding shortfalls, classroom overcrowding, outdated texts, dilapidated buildings, teacher turnover, increasing teacher workloads, and stagnant wages, to focus on the question of whether any teachers appeared to be advocating Communism. Though Kassoy repeatedly criticized these manifestations of McCarthyism, he was never blacklisted. His work can also be found in the collections of the Museum of Modern Art, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York Public Library, and Fennimore House Museum.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
8507521
- Alton S. Tobey - 90th Birthday Celebration (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bernard Kassoy (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous Slides (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 1990-1991 -- The Smithy Show (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Amazon Cruise - 1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Amazon Cruise - 1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Color Negs - 35 mm - 1984-1986; 1992-1993; 1973, 1975, 1973-1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Rollei Test at VCCA - Honey Video - Taping in studio (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Scope and Contents
  35 mm negs; proofs; misc.
- Misc. Negs. & proof sheets (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Best Pictorial - slides & negatives (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Sri Lanka - negs. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Color negs; Misc.; 1994-1995; 1991, 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- WW2 photo album (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Europe -- 1960-1962 (1 of 6) (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Europe 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Europe 1960 (3 of 6) (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous -- in park; at Antioch (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Grass fire 1966; Moss Aiev Dancers - Portraits - Honey; Walk in park - 1965-1966 (5 of 6) (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous -- Airport; Sept. 1968 - Folk Dancing; 1965 (6 of 6), 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Europe 1960 (1 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Europe 1960 (2 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Europe 1960 (3 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 9)
- USSR Cruise, 1967; Amazon Cruise, 1994 -- edited 1998 (1 of 3), 1967-1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- USSR Cruise, 1967; Amazon Cruise, 1994 -- edited 1998 (2 of 3), 1967-1998 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- USSR Cruise, 1967; Amazon Cruise, 1994 - edited 1998 (3 of 3), 1967-1998 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- England, Belgium, France, Italy, Spain 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- England, Belgium, France, Italy, Spain 1969-1970 (2 of 4) (Box 3, Folder 14)
- England, Belgium, France, Italy, Spain 1969-1970 (3 of 4) (Box 3, Folder 15)
- England, Belgium, France, Italy, Spain 1969-1970 (4 of 4) (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Roman Bronze Works; Swatonah Waterfront; Misc. (1 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Leningrad; Palermo; California - 1974; Yosemite - 1974; Misc.; Israel; Great Paintings (2 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Barbados; City Island; X-mas @ Lou Cohen; 6th Floor Party; New Years Eve; Misc. (3 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Sicily - 1976; Pond (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Pond - cont. (2 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Pond - cont.; Turkey (3 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Woodstock (1 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Misc. - 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Honey's 60th Birthday Party 1978 (3 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Cuba - 1982 (1 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Cuba -- 1982 (2 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Cuba -- 1982 (3 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Milles Garden; Miscellaneous 1967; Guardian Picnic, Oct. 1966, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Western Trip 1966; National Parks 1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Merry Silver Gown 1966; Viet Protest; U. of Colorado, 1966; Evander boat ride 1966; Expo 1967, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Photo negatives (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Elder Horkel at Alfred Univ. 5/22-6/1/1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Twin kittens for Jill; 2006 Lehman Awards at Bert Brooks Seder at Merry's [photos and negs] (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Seder at KP 4/23/2005; ASCA Award at 5/11/2005 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Birth of Felice LeMarca; Hawaii 1998 - more (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Panama, Poland, Upstate Misc.; VCCA, London (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Misc. photos (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Vacation photos (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Good Van Cort Pond shots & Misc. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Star Chopper Cruise (9/24-10/09); Honey's 90th Birthday --- negatives (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Bernie 90th Birthday Celebration; Misc. (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Barbados; St. Vincent; Santarem; Boca de Valeria Eco Park (duplicates) (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Misc. Prints & Negs 2001 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Cruise - 3/26-4/5/1991; Cruise on N. Amsterdam; Cruise to Hawaii 1998 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Seder at Sheila's; Van Costible - reflections, etc. at the lake (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Sonora Museum - 1/1992; Aaron Olshan Show; Amazon Cruise - 19/1994 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Negatives -- New Year Card - 2000; Honey's carving (2000-2007) (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Several "Special Occasion" cards; March 3, 1962, Guggenheim Museum & Times Square; portfolio of Bernie's Business Cards (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Pilobolus (negs); Waterbird (contact card); 4/23/2005; Misc. greeting cards; Honey summer 2005 (neg.); memories on board - Nieuw Amsterdam; County House (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Honey working at Tallix (5/10/2002); Honey show at Pioneer -- July 2002 [index & negs] (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Star Clipper Cruise -- 10/2004 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Seler at Sheila's; Joel, Peter, Honey, Honey birthday flowers (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Painting slides (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Photo stamp (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Print strips (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Personal slides of Greece & Rome (1 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 32)
  listing included in this folder
- Personal slides of Greece & Rome (2 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Personal slides of Greece & Rome (3 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 34)
- FSSF Reunion - Helena Montana - 8/19-22/1992 [duplicates] (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Assorted batches of negatives, - batches have some labeling (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Assorted batches of negatives -- batches have some labeling (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Duplicate Photos (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Photos of a flower & a horse (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Panama Canal Cruise 1996 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Bolton Labor Day Picnic; Sheila & Sara at Tobey's birthday (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Photo negatives (Box 5, Folder 8)
- French River Cruise -- May 4, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Honey - sculpture - 'Farewell' negatives; Bernie - 3 new oil (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Polish Trip - Cralow Auscwhich (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Krakow Kobushova - Duplicates (May 1995) (Box 5, Folder 12)
- At M & R's 3/2/1998 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- 80th Birthday Party (Box 5, Folder 14)
- French River Cruise - 2 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Boulder Colorado - Oct. 1997 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Miscellaneous photos (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Butternut Hill & Nadelman's - Photo negatives (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Contents of a 3-ring binder - Memorabilia from Bernie's time in the Military, 1942-1944 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Praktika slides 8/1996-2/1997, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Assorted slides 1997-1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Assorted slides May-June 1999 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Assorted slides July-Oct. 1999 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Misc. prints, slides, negatives 1991, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  (contents of a
- Female nudes (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Photos of rural and urban landscapes (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Slides, prints 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  contents of a 3 ring binder
- Slides of sculptures (1 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Slides of sculptures (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Europe 1969 (cont.); Bronze Casting; Yucatan 1972; Caravan Show (2 of 2), 1969-1972 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Italy 1968; Snow 1970; Europe 1969, 1968-1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Honey rejects - Clay Maquette rejects (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Thurber drawings (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Misc. slides, negs. 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Negs 110 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Assorted - misc. photos (contents of a 3-ring binder) (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Various slides (see listing on 1 of 3) (1 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Various slides (see listing on 1 of 3) (2 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Various slides (see listing on 1 of 3) (3 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Various slides (see listing of 1 of 3) (1 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Various slides (see listing of 1 of 3) (2 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Various slides (see listing of 1 of 3) (3 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Various event slides (see listing of 1 of 3) (1 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Various event slides (see listing of 1 of 3) (2 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Various event slides (see listing of 1 of 3) (3 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Pietrasanta (1 of 2) (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Pietrasanta (2 of 2) (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Slides of pictures of artwork (contents of a 3-ring binder) (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Art 308 -- negatives and some photographs (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Negatives at WARO or AEA (contents of a 3-ring binder) (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Contact sheets and negatives (contents of a 3-ring binder) (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Negatives of photos of Bernie's etchings and woodcut prints (contents of a 3 ring binder) (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Photographs and slides of Bernie's artwork (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous photos on slides - listing and description included (contents of 3 ring binder) (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Sculpture and Works on Paper by Hortense Kassoy (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Unlabeled 3-ring binder contents - Vacation photos? - glass negatives, photograph negatives, and a few photographs (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Combination of vacation photos, artwork, etc. on slides (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Negatives of paintings (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Woodcut photograph negatives - Ross Robbins portrait, etc. (contents of a 3-ring binder) (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Various Art Show photograph negatives (contents of a 3-ring binder) (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Slides at show - Night Fires - Pastels - Water Colors - Drawings (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Negatives and slides of photographs of art projects --- some negatives very brittle (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Select watercolors & pastels (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Student M & A work 1960's (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Slides -- 1986-1988; Water colors & Pastels 1993-1997, 1986-1997 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Nudity. (Restricted) (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Pilot 6 negatives; Bruno Institute, Lehman College - Archive photos (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Self portrait of David (digital photo of the original oil painting) & copies of some negatives, and a couple contact strips (Box 13, Folder 3)
  original oil painting done in Jan. 1946, digital photo taken in 2008